I'll call this to order.
Um, do a roll. Are you doing roll call?
>> Sure.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> I'm here.
>> Mr.
>> Here,
>> well, I'm not a member, but I'm here.
the mayor.
>> Okay, thank you very much. Um, yeah,
this is uh meeting of the government
study transition committee and we're
here to I guess we'll start by hearing
an update on the administrative code.
>> Sure. So, council's met uh three times
um as a committee of the whole. One was
to uh receive information from me sort
of an education as to what the charter
required regarding the admin code uh how
the admin code how we proposed to do an
admin code process um in terms of
bringing it to them in two separate
components um with the reiteration that
in all cases what I was bringing to them
were a starting point for their
discussions in other words this is
ultimately uh city council's
administrative code not the solicitors
not the administr rations. Um, but
bringing my experience both with the uh
government study commission and work
obviously with the city since 1994 to
try and make some recommendations as
starting points. Um, we held two
sessions on the first half and it's not
in order but one half of the
administrative code on June 17th and
July 15th. The topics in the sections
presented to council during those two
sessions included the general powers of
uh of the city and powers of council and
administration. Um sort of just a repeat
of the charter um salaries of elected
officials which um Mr. Mcan if you
recall was left specifically to uh city
council to cover. um budgets, finance
and accounting including fund management
policy, debt management policy,
investment policy, accounting policy, uh
procurement, disposal of city property,
uh insurance and bonding, records and
record retention.
Um we we had a little bit of discussion
on a portion regarding confidential
information which uh ultimately is
really about keeping information
confidential that it belongs to somebody
else. Um whether that ultimately gets
folded into the ethics code or not, it
can be a standalone or part of the
ethics code depending on how council
decides to proceed. Um we have two more
meetings scheduled uh for the second
section of this uh on August 19th and
September 16th. Um what will be
presented to the committee of the whole
uh are sections that will cover topics
um along the lines of organizational
structure which includes and you recall
the charter requires that we do that um
all of the departments officials, police
and fire bureaus, city council. Uh so
this will govern a lot of a lot of some
thing a lot of things we already have in
our ordinances but may be tweaked
modified or changed now that we're
folding it into one comprehensive
document entitled the admin code. Um
ordinances and resolutions. So the
methodology by which ordinances and
resolutions are adopted. um forfeiture
of office. Again, if you recall, the
charter left uh to council the uh
requirement to develop um the procedure
for forefeiter of office and forefeiter
uh occurs under certain set
circumstances which are prescribed in
the charter itself. Um section on
boards, commissions and authorities and
again that's similar to to council. It's
a it's appointment, approval, terms, um
removal, all of those types of things.
Um
basic terms to at least start us
thinking about the ethics code. Again,
we need to receive the recommendations
of the ethics commission, but there will
be some basic information in there.
things like we start to get into at
least talking about a conflict of
interest, but these are really more
placeholders until that discussion um
widens after the ethics commission gets
up and running, which is starting next
week on August 7th. Um employment and
human resources. So that's going to uh
cover all the sections dealing with uh
basic employment, HR requirements, uh
civil service, electronic signatures,
municipal leans and claims, and the
publicly accessible website. Um so
hopefully we'll have uh uh two good
sessions. Uh the session in August will
meet will be me going through those
sections just like we did the last time.
Uh sort of explaining their derivation
where they came from, whether they came
from um existing city ordinances,
whether they came from, hey, the third
class city code did this and did it
well, so you might want to continue it.
Um whether they came from the charter.
uh and then uh more in-depth
conversation at the second meeting in
September. Um
and uh again announcing to the public
there will be a methodology for
submitting questions on the code and
obtaining copies which we have through
the engage platform similar to what we
do with the budget process where
citizens can uh submit questions
regarding the drafts that have been
presented. So that's uh really the
update on the admin code. The goal is
still to adopt it before the end of the
year, preferably in October if we can.
That will depend in large part on what
happens with the ethics commission and
the recommendations regarding the ethics
code.
Okay,
sounds great.
uh how and and you've been involved. I
mean, you feel like it h how do you feel
like the process has gone so far?
>> Um yes, from a council perspective, I do
feel that we're on the right track and
um you know, excited to see how the
ethics commission um turns up and then
from there, I think um the city and the
solicitor have us on the right track to
get this all complete by um the end of
the year.
>> Right. because I think we the I was just
thinking about this after listening in
on the uh the most recent meeting. So
the the deadline for the ethics
commission is 12 months.
>> Well, the ethics code is
>> the ethics code is 12 months from
>> from the from the effective date of
>> of the charter
>> charter.
>> So January 1st,
>> correct?
>> Okay. Not not election day.
>> Correct.
>> That's I was
>> the charter itself is a non-existing
document until its effective date which
is December 1st.
>> Okay. So, ethics code must be by
December 31st
and should be we do we still have an
expectation that it'll be complete well
in advance of that.
>> The goal is to have um the entire admin
code including the ethics code. So, the
ethics code really belongs inside the
admin code when you think about the
topics we've discussed and where it
would lie. Y
>> um so yes, the goal is to to try and
have that all done quite frankly before
budget is adopted. Yeah,
>> in November
>> jumped ahead a little bit. So, I mean,
so, you know, from what it sounds like,
we're comfortably ahead of the actual
deadline for the administrative code.
>> Yes.
>> And most likely comfortably ahead of our
sort of agreed upon deadline
uh before the end of the year.
>> Yeah. And I mean, I I I fully anticipate
that, you know, the ethics commission is
a recommending body obviously for the
for this code. They don't draft or adopt
the code. They make recommendations. Um,
and you know, the nice thing about the
admin code Yes.
>> Are are we sort of slipping into the
next agenda item? Yeah.
>> Yeah, that sounds fine.
>> Yep.
>> Um, the nice thing about this process is
that the administrative code and the
ethics code are adopted by ordinance.
>> Y
>> um and are therefore always modifiable
at any time by city council by
ordinance. So, I expect them to be
living and breathing documents which
will undergo periodic review and most
likely periodic change. So, you know,
council's first uh incarnation of an
admin code might change over the years
and and I think that's what's going to
happen with the ethics code as well. I
think we're going to get something
pretty good in place and then as
experience dictates, changes will be
made to that. So, I don't anticipate the
deadlines being problematic because of
council's ability to make this a living
breathing document.
>> Okay.
>> Uh and the ethics commission is meeting
next week, August 7th, for the first
time. um that the the topics for
discussion at that meeting will include
um uh the appointing bodies left it to
the members to determine their terms. So
if you recall their terms have to be
staggered.
>> So there'll be some discussion about
that. Um there'll be an introduction
from me into the requirements of the
ethics code is set forth in the charter
and that's article 12 of the charter and
there's some specific requirements that
they need to focus on in making their
recommendations.
Um, and then we'll talk about meeting
schedule and the next steps to getting
towards those recommendations. I
anticipate that I'll be providing them
with a couple of ethics codes that the
Government Study Commission spent some
time looking at.
>> Um,
two in particular, uh, um, Pennsylvania
Economy League reminded me those were
the two that the commission focused on
most, which were, uh, East's and
Pittsburgh's. um with Pittsburgh's
probably being a little bit more than
what's needed, but Easton's being a kind
of a good sort of softer landing point,
but both having really valuable
information from which to look.
>> Um we'll also uh introduce them to the
state ethics code because obviously
that's highly relevant in this
particular case.
>> Okay.
Then just I mean now I'm going to sort
of rewind to the earlier topic. I mean,
do you were you know, I did listen in or
watch um
at least two and maybe I think all three
of the meetings. I mean, would you was
there any were there any topics that
seemed to generate a lot of questions or
a lot of discussion? It felt like
>> uh in the first section, no. Um uh we we
all uh we being uh those at the city
administration who have had some input
into the second section or quite frankly
into the entirety of the admin code
draft. Um expect that there will be a
lot more discussion um in the next
section um when we start talking about
um government official um whether that
be elected, appointed or hired behavior
which is ethics code provisions. When we
start talking about council meetings
themselves, when we start talking about
forefeiture of office, um when we talk
about a process for adopting ordinances
and resolutions, um structure of council
meetings, we expect that there will be
>> um a stronger a stronger sense of
discussion there because the council
members are far more familiar with those
items than maybe they are on some of the
financial policies. And do do I have it
right? Also included in what's upcoming
is boards, commissions, and authorities.
>> And will that include,
you know, do we expect the lineup of
boards, commissions, and authorities to
change as a result of this process or do
we not or is too early to say?
>> So, it's not going to change as a result
of this process. Um, I do believe the
administration is going to be making a
proposal to consolidate a number of
boards. Mhm.
>> Um but that wouldn't really happen
through the admin code. It's going to
happen through separate legislation.
>> Okay.
>> Um because it it involves you know
multiple boards which have multiple
pieces of legislation. Um we do have a
constitutional requirement with respect
to ordinances to have sort of a single
topic. Um so I think the board
consolidation um the discussion will
certainly come up during this segment
but the legislation to enact it will
probably be coming a little later.
>> Okay.
Thank you.
>> Uh my only question with the um updates
on the ethics commission is uh I know
that they are going to be setting the
schedule for when they meet, but how
frequently will they be meeting?
>> So that that's up to them to determine.
Um part of that will be uh uh in terms
of providing you with you being council
with recommendations. I think they're
going to have to determine how much they
feel they need to meet versus how much
they're going to do in sort of
individual work like we did on the
government study commission and then
come together and discuss. Um they will
also be required to meet if there are
ultimately um investigations or um uh
charges that they have to that they have
to review. Of course, we have to create
the process for doing that through the
through the admin code first. But once
that happens, uh there's no requirement
in the charter for how often they have
to meet. They have educational
requirements under the charter to
educate uh city employees, um elected
officials, appointed officials, and the
public as to the ethical requirements of
their government officials. Um what that
looks like is something that they're
going to have to determine over time.
>> And once they do reach that
determination, would that be put into
the admin code? uh if they want to
mandate how often they meet. It could be
um yes and that's again why this is an
ordinance. So it would be an amendment
to the
>> concludes my questions.
>> Okay, great. Thank you. Um I don't have
any further questions. You feel like you
covered what you wanted here us to hear
about today?
>> I do. Yes.
>> Okay. Um the only other well the the
next agenda item is uh just you know a
request I made to have a report on the
promotion of these meetings. And I guess
I'll start by saying you know I feel
like one of you know I think you know
feels like you know not you know of
comparable importance to the future of
the city as the as the home rule charter
and wanting to make sure that you know
we're doing the best that we can to
alert the public to it and make sure
that the community understands the
importance and significance of this and
you know the hopes that we're getting
engagement
as much engagement as possible.
>> Well, I mean, I have Wyatt, our Wyatt
Bar, our communication director, is
here, but I but I can tell you that
we've required with all the legal
requirements.
>> Yep.
>> Um, you know, there's only so much you
can do. Um, so we've had now three
meetings uh of the council. We've had a
meeting scheduled of the ethics
commission. We have two more meetings of
council scheduled. Um, every meeting
gets advertised in the Lancaster
newspaper. every meeting agenda gets
posted. Um they get not only advertised
in the newspaper, but now it's posted on
our website. It's posted here. Um
we're going to continue to do that
obviously. Um the meetings have been
live streamed. Uh so there's, you know,
again, which is not every board,
commission, and authority is going
through that.
>> Um so, you know, and then once we get to
the point where there's an ordinance to
adopt, it will go through its normal
advertising requirement again. So more
legal notice there. Um there will be a
public workshop if you recall um the the
uh charter requires that on the ethics
code component. So that will be yet
another meeting um that will be uh noted
by advertisement. I've already indicated
we have uh a platform up for questions
on the admin code um as we present it
each time. Uh and that will continue
throughout the process as well. Wyatt,
have I missed anything?
Okay, that's great. I mean, what you
know, what's your sort of observation
about
participation from the public at the
meetings that you've had so far?
>> So, the the the I mean, keep in mind
that these are being conducted many in
many ways, Mr. McGrant, just like the
>> um discussion components of the
government study commission.
>> Yep.
>> So, uh you know, there is discussion,
but there's not It's not like they're
taking motions and saying, "Okay, now
does somebody want to comment on a
motion?" There there's the opportunity
to comment at the end of each of the
work sessions. Y
>> um we've had some comments, limited, but
some um I think people are paying the
people that are paying attention are
asking good questions.
>> Um and again, I think part of it is
going to be there's there's built-in
time once we've done both sections of
this
>> for people to have more time to look at
it sort of in whole. And you know that
it's not an easy thing to comprehend all
of this and to understand the
implications of all of it. Um, as I've
indicated at some of the meetings with
council, there's not a lot there is some
there's not a lot that's brand new. Like
a lot of this is carryovers from what's
been done with some expansions. There's
change some changes necessitated by the
charter itself. Um and you know in the
next section there will be some new
things proposed. Um there'll be some new
things that I I'm excited to to actually
introduce to council particularly in uh
for example in the section on ordinances
and some some I think requirements on
council and staff to to better present
uh ordinances and to better better keep
the public apprised of why the ordinance
is being adopted. um what it's intended
to accomplish, how it will be tracked.
Um so some some better practices that
aren't necessarily required by any of
the uh codes like the third class city
code, township codes, etc. So
>> yep. Okay. Thank you. And to add, I um
yeah, to add in my council comments post
of when we have these meetings, I do um
make council aware of, you know, what
we've been talking about in these
meetings and the public aware and um
when our next scheduled meeting is. So,
I've been trying to as the
representative of council to this body,
I've been trying to take this back to
council at the next meeting after we
meet each time and also let us know and
let them know and the public know when
the next scheduled transition committee
meeting is.
>> Okay, that's great. So, and and the
reason I I mean there's three things on
my mind related to this, you know, and
and the reason I asked to include it on
the agenda. one is, you know, throughout
the drafting process especially, um, I
feel like there were many instances
where Pennsylvania Economy League and
and you, Mr. Hammer, were like, "Okay,
well, that's advising the commissioners
that a topic that was of interest was
more appropriately, you know, for future
discussion in part of the admin code."
So, I want to make sure that we're
reminding the community, including the
home rule study commissioners, that
around those topics, you know, their
best opportunity to weigh in on those
things is still in front of us.
>> And and keep in mind that like there
will be opportunities for significant
question and comment before this is
adopted. So, these are just work
sessions.
>> Yeah.
>> And then we still have to go through the
formal two reading process just like any
other ordinance.
>> And and that's my second point, which is
I feel like, you know,
we had as the end of the home rule study
commission's process approached is when
we started to see some more robust
attendance. So I'm hoping that we can
look forward to that with the admin
code. I guess time will tell. And then
also just thinking about some of the
work that was done on the public
engagement committee and some of the
things that we tried to do above and
beyond the the legal requirements to
make sure that it got some visibility on
the city's social media channels and and
some other ways. So hope I guess I'm
bringing up you know with the hope that
we can find an opportunity to do as much
of that as as reasonable.
>> I'll I'll certainly pass that on to the
administration.
>> Yep. And I'll and that's that was my
purpose in adding it to the agenda today
is to is to make that plea so that as
the rest of this unfolds you know above
and beyond the legal requirements that
if there's opportunities to to promote
it in some of the ways that might
connect with people be beyond that that
we're giving ourselves the best chance
for that.
>> Yep.
>> So
>> yeah take that back to Tom's team.
>> Yep. Thanks. Yeah. Thank you. Um, I mean
I think that that concludes my interest
in that agenda item unless either of you
had anything to add to that.
Okay. Um, so now we have an opportunity
for public comment.
We have some public here.
>> Thank you, Wyatt.
[Music]
Tony Dastra, 700 block of New Holland
Avenue. Um, so
I'm here because I'm really frustrated
at the original draft. Um, I don't think
that we are handling this transition
completely appropriately, although that
is not entirely exclusively the
responsibility of the people here today.
Um, I do feel like the administrative
code is observing the powers of the
ethics commission because even though
the charter outlines certain things that
are prohibited, this charter still also
requires that the ethics commode code is
written by the ethics commission and
adopted by council and there's a public
meeting prior. So having anything
related to the ethics section of the
charter included in the admin code makes
me go, well, is it now subject to the
same rules? Does it nullify those rules?
It puts it in a real state of question
for me because this charter is the
guiding document for the city. So when
we have these things built into the
admin code and not the ethics code, it
makes me question why we're having these
meetings rushed so we can get this done
by the I shouldn't say these meetings
are rushed, but these meetings to rush
an admin code by the end of this year
when the ethics code has a shorter
timeline and is required by the end of
this year. We have six more months for
the admin code. So, it's kind of
backwards how things are operating. And
what y'all really need to be advocating
for more than the promotion of these
meetings is getting the ethics
commission moving. They have a deadline
to meet sooner than you guys on this on
the admin code on the administration
code section. So, um, look, I don't
expect that we're ever going to have a
room full of people to discuss these
issues. I mean, Jesus, look at how I'm
addressed right now. Like, I got these
crazy socks on. I'm coming from work.
I'm biking here. like otherwise I would
have respected you guys enough to put my
suit on. Okay. Um and respected the
subject matter as well.
But yeah, like I I'm I'm really
frustrated and I'm hoping that you guys
listen to me that we need to article 5
needs to come out. That needs to be like
recommend it to the ethics commission
for their consideration, but it needs to
come out of the admin code. All the all
the sections of the code relating to the
ethics of chapter 12 of the charter need
to be handled by the ethics commission
which as I understand has not met yet.
They've only been appointed. We should
all be concerned by that right now
because we're h more than halfway
through the year.
So they have five months to get
something to you, Mr. Amed, and the rest
of council.
That should be a concern to y'all here
and to the public as a whole.
Okay.
>> I'm really upset. Thank you though for
listening.
>> Thanks for coming. You I can't remember
if you were in the room at the point the
the there is a meeting of the ethics
commission
August 7th.
>> Next Tuesday.
>> Next Thursday, excuse me.
>> Thursday. Okay.
>> So that is
>> getting started.
>> Okay.
>> Appreciate your comments and
keep we will be mindful of that as this
proceeds. Any
other
comments from the public?
All right, then I'll welcome a motion to
adjurnn.
>> Motion to adjurnn. Um
>> in favor of that. Thank you very much.